# 大家好 今天來摘點隔壁村大叔家的這個香菇哇
Hi everyone! Today we come to the uncle in our neighbouring village for his shiitake mushrooms.
# 這個香菇 很漂亮的哦 你看
The mushrooms, are really pretty. Look!
# 要摘到腳來 (註︰未摘過香菇，不太明白)
You need to pick the stem.
# 很香
It smells good!
# 這個腳 腳到摘掉
The stems, the stems need to be taken away.
# 哎呀
Haya!
# 哎呀 好結實啊
Aya! It sticks firmly.
# 哇 這裡藏了一個
Wa! One is hidden here.
# 哎呀 那麼大的
Aya! It's so big.
# 這個可以把它
This can be,
# 把它摘掉
can be picked.
# 你看 這個大的
Look! This one is large.
# 哎喲
Ayo!
# 哇 這兩個
Wa! These two...
# 嗯 把它擰下來
Um! Let me twist them off.
# 裡面藏了一個好大個的
A really huge one is hidden inside.
# 很香哦 這個
It smells really good!
# 這種椴木香菇 種起來很麻煩的
Growing shiitake mushrooms on this kind of linden wood needs tremendous effort.
# 它第一年的話長一點點
You can never get more than a tiny little bit in the first year,
# 第2年的話長得沒那麼多
and not so much more in the second year.
# 第3年的話長好多
But there will be a lot in the third year.
# 所以種起來特別麻煩
It's really too much a trouble,
# 現在農村人都不喜歡種這個啦
that the people in the villages nowadays don't want to grow them anymore.
# 因為周期太長啦
Cuz the period is far too long.
# 但是
But
# 有些
some
# 有些農戶閒置在家裡沒事做的話
some farmers still grow them,
# 就可以種一點這個
if they have nothing to do at home,
# 也可以換一點錢回來
in exchange for some money.
# 因為這個賣得特別貴
Cuz these can be sold at a very good price.
# 這個木頭上種出來的香菇 特別香
These mushrooms growing on the wood have a very significant aroma.
# 特別好吃 但是那產量很低哦
It tastes exceptionally good. But the yield is very low.
# 那個木屑種出來的那種啊 就是那個菌包
Those grown on the sawdust, I mean the mushroom kit,
# 包起來 一袋袋的那個
those in packages,
# 種出來的沒那麼好吃
are not as tasty as these ones.
# 但是它一年四季都會長
But they're growing throughout the year.
# 它那 大棚上種 可以種得到 (註︰有種過香菇的人可以解釋下嗎？)
It can be grown, grown on a shed.
# 但我們這邊的話 它的
But our mushrooms here, the
# 採摘期呀
the harvesting period,
# 就摘三個 三四個月左右 就沒有啦
lasts only for three, three or four months, and that's it.
# 就是 冬天 這個冬天過了就沒有啦
That's the winter. After winter, no more.
# 但是 可以烘乾後可以放到 放到一兩年
But, it can be parched. Then it can be stored for a year or two.
# 烘乾
Parched
# 很香的哦
It smells really good.
# 你看 這裡面好多哇
Look! There are a lot inside.
# 還 還不大 還沒長大
Still, still not that large. They've not grown up.
# 大叔都已經摘了
But the uncle has already picked,
# 100多斤啦
more than 50 kg.
# 就這種曬乾的
This is dried.
# 你看
Look!
# 這都是一個一個的 都被摘掉啦
These were the mushrooms. But they've already been picked.
# 都被大叔全部摘掉啦
They've all been picked by the uncle.
# 好 摘了好多啦
A...he's picked a lot.
# 看都看得出來
It's very obvious.
# 挑大的摘
Let me choose a big one.
# 摘了那麼一點點 夠一餐就可以啦
So I've picked just a tiny little bit here. It's alright. Enough for a meal.
# 你看 這些就是我們剛摘回來的
Look! These are what we've just picked.
# 這兩袋是我們買 找大叔買的
And these two bags are bought, bought from the uncle.
# 這個是烤乾了的
These are parched.
# 等下我去抓兄弟的雞過來
I'll get the a chicken from my buddy later,
# 把它燉啦
and make a stew out of it.
# 小雞燉蘑菇
Chicken and shiitake mushroom stew
# 好香啊
It smells really good!
# 誒 抓了一個
Ey! Here's one!
# 你先抓穩來
Hold it tight first.
# 這一個好像好小誒
This one seems to be very small.
# 再抓一個
One more!
# 來 這裡
Yea! Here!
# 這個也才 兩斤多 不大的
This one is also, just slightly more than a kilogram, not large.
# 剛好兩個
So we have two.
# 搞個大鍋
We need a big wok.
# 這個隻雞殺好啦
The two chickens are ready now.
# 很好哦
They're really small,
# 才兩三斤而已
just slightly more than a kilogram.
# 拿個大鍋來燉
We need a big wok.
# 你看 等一下我就把它燉
Look! I'll cook them in a minute.
# 先把它砍碎來
Let me chop them into pieces first.
# 這個稍微砍大塊一點
I'll chop into slightly larger pieces,
# 大塊一點
larger.
# 太小塊啦
It won't taste good,
# 不好吃
if it's too small.
# 脖子那麼長 (註︰原字幕沒有)
What a long neck!
# 把這個乾香菇的屁股啊 要把它剪掉
The butts of the dried mushroom, need to be cut away.
# 不用放那麼多的
We don't need too many.
# 放一點就行啦
Just a bit would be enough.
# 這樣就夠啦 我們去洗一下
It's enough! Let's wash them.
# 可以
Alright!
# 把這個香菇放下去
I now put in the mushrooms.
# 放點生薑
Put some ginger.
# 這薑 放下去
Put the ginger, into the wok.
# 加點水
Put some water.
# 誒呦 一大鍋哦
Ayo! A whole big wok!
# 這樣燉一個小時 一個小時就夠啦
Boil it for an hour, for an hour and then it's done.
# 摘了半個小時啦
It's half an hour already.
# 哇
Wa!
# 好香哦
It smells so good!
# 真的好香 兄弟家的雞
It smells really good! Buddy's chicken,
# 兩隻哦
not one but two!
# 還有大叔家的香菇
And uncle's shiitake mushrooms.
# 哇
Wa!
# 味道杠杠滴 (註︰這又是甚麼？)
C'est délicieux!
# 加點鹽
Put some salt.
# 嗯 夠啦
Um! It's enough.
# 先嘗一下這個香菇
Let me try the mushroom.
# 嗯 好香啊
Um! It smells wonderful!
# 香菇熟啦
The mushrooms are alright now.
# 我看下雞肉有沒有熟
Let me see if the chicken is done.
# 我撒點葱花下去
I put some shredded spring onions.
# 看上去更有食欲
It looks much more appetizing.
# 哇 真的好香啊 你看這個汁 濃濃的
Wa! It smells marvelous! Look at the soup! It's thick and rich.
# 啊 先搞個雞翅吃一下
Ah! Let me have a chicken wing.
# 夾不起來
It's hard to take.
# 嗯 可以哦
Um! Not bad!
# 好香啊(註︰「香」字出現得太多了，改一下)
Wonderful!
# 哇! 這個真的好香啊
Wa! It's really really nice.
# 它這個香菇 雞肉上融入了香菇的味道
The mushrooms, the flavour of the mushrooms is blended with the chicken.
# 真的 好久沒吃過那麼好吃的
Frankly speaking, we haven't had such good food for a long time already.
# 嗯 小狗 這骨頭給你吃
Um! Doggy! The bone is for you.
# 這個 蘑菇
Have a, mushroom,
# 最大的蘑菇
the largest mushroom.
# 嗯 蘑菇中含有雞肉的味道
Um! There's a note of chicken in the mushroom.
# 這很燙
It's very hot.
# 你要不要雞肉
You want some chicken?
# 要不要
Do you?
# 你要不要香菇
You want mushroom?
# 要不要 很燙的哦
Do you? It's really hot!
# 等下冷了我再給你吃啊 哈
I'll give you when it cools down, okay?
# 吃個雞爪 這雞爪很好吃的哦
Let me have a chicken foot. The chicken foot is really tasty.
# 有點燙
It's a bit hot.
# 小黑
Blacky!
# 好啦 今天的視頻到這裡啦 老弟們都等不急啦
Alright! The video ends here. Our younger brothers can't wait any longer.
# 到他兩個
It's their turns.
# 開工開工開工開工 開吃咯
Go, go, go, go! Meal time!
# 要不要 (註︰劉星辰沒有字幕)
You want some?
# 啊
Ah?
# 雞 很好吃的
The chicken is really tasty!
# 來來來來來 通通都有啊
C'mon, c'mon, c'mon! Everybody has a share.
# 好香的好香的 好香啊
It's really really good.
It's so nice!